<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>King Charles his glory, and rebels shame. Collonel Hevvson. To a pleasant new tune: Or, The crost couple.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B06870</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.20.f.4[36]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99884935</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99884935</idno>
            <idno type="VID">182706</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B06870)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 182706)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; A4:2[36])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>King Charles his glory, and rebels shame. Collonel Hevvson. To a pleasant new tune: Or, The crost couple.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill. (woodcut).  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The words "Collonel Hevvson." are separated by the woodcut illustration.</note>
                  <note>Verse: "CHARLES the first was a Noble King ..."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Cf. Wing K553 which gives title word "rebells".</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Hewson, John, d. 1662 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ballads, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="ballad">
            <pb facs="tcp:182706:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->
            <head>King CHARLES his Glory, And REBELS Shame.<figure>
                  <head>Collonel Hevvſon.</head>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <opener>To a pleaſant New Tune: Or, <hi>The Croſt Couple.</hi>
            </opener>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>CHARLES</hi> the firſt was a Noble King,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fa la la la la la.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His Fame thorow all the world did ring,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fa la</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>But in this he was to blame</l>
               <l>That after all his pomp and Fame,</l>
               <l>To loſe himſelf at a Scottiſh Game.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Twas but a fooliſh thing.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He was a Prince of courage ſtout,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>Although his Glaſs was ſoon run out,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>Behind him he left a Noble Stock,</l>
               <l>May give Traitors a handſom knock,</l>
               <l>For making a King ſubmit to a block</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Good things may wind about,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>then</hi> Huſons <hi>Eye goes ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The blood that he loſt as I ſuppoſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>Caus'd fire to riſe in <hi>Olivers</hi> Noſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>This Ruling Noſe did bear ſuch a ſway,</l>
               <l>It caſt ſuch a heat and ſhining ray,</l>
               <l>That <hi>England</hi> ſcarce knew night from day</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Good Lord preſerve his houſe.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This <hi>Oliver</hi> was of <hi>Huntington,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>Born he was but a Brewers Son,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>He ſoon forſook the Dray and Sling,</l>
               <l>And counted a Brew-houſe a petty thing,</l>
               <l>Unto the Stately Throne of a King.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>It far ſurpaſt a Tun.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But <hi>Oliver</hi> had a heart of Gall,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>To murther his Prince at <hi>White-hall,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>He ſwares whoſoever is over the Main,</l>
               <l>Whether a French King or of Spain,</l>
               <l>Yet in <hi>England</hi> no King ſhall Raign.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lest</hi> Nol <hi>himſelf ſhould fall.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Duke <hi>Humphrey</hi> was the firſt Protector,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond the next Projector,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>Then thirdly <hi>Oliver</hi> he took place,</l>
               <l>But <hi>Lucifer</hi> ſoon removed his Grace,</l>
               <l>And ſet up yong <hi>Dick</hi> the fool of his race.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dick loved a Cup of Nector</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No ſooner was <hi>Dickee</hi> got up to the throne,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>But he conſidered 'twas none of his own,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>And ſtaring this way, and that way about,</l>
               <l>Deſirous to be reſolved of a doubt,</l>
               <l>In comes <hi>Lambert</hi> and turns him out.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la;</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So</hi> Lamberts <hi>courage was ſhown.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fleetwood</hi> deſirous of the place,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>Sends forth <hi>Lambert</hi> the Scots to face,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>But in the ſtrength of his deſire,</l>
               <l>When he did intend poor Jocky to fire,</l>
               <l>His men forſook him and left him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th mire.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ay and that was his diſgrace.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus you perceive how ſome do riſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>And even ſurmount the Aerie Skies.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>But when they are up they ſhall have a fall,</l>
               <l>Witneſs <hi>Fleetwood,</hi> blind <hi>Hewſon,</hi> and all</l>
               <l>The Ragged Rout of a Coblers Stall.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Would</hi> Hewſon <hi>had both his eyes.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When Dame Fortune caſteth a frown,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>Theſe upſtart Gallants fall headlong down,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>I could wiſh they would view their own ſtate,</l>
               <l>And Repent before tis to late,</l>
               <l>For fear leſt a Gibbet will be their laſt fate,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Or whipping about the Town.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Clear <hi>Whitehall</hi> of Lobſter and Gooſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>Caſt RUMPS and Kidneys out of the houſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>Fetch in <hi>Charls</hi> from over the Main,</l>
               <l>Make Wars with <hi>Dutch</hi> men, peace with <hi>Spain,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then we ſhall have money and Trading again.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And then we care not a Lowſe.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Citizens look to your hits, I ſay,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>Let no Cobler preach nor pray,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tom</hi> Coblers gone the Lord knows whether,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lambert</hi> and he I hope are together,</l>
               <l>Now fetch in the King we ſhall have fair weather.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whip Coblers run away.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Blind <hi>Huſon</hi> was not over kind,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>To run and leave his men behind,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>fa la,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               <l>I wiſh we could find him by the ſcent,</l>
               <l>There's neither Law nor RUMP Parliament</l>
               <l>Should ſave him from death to give us content.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Good People pitty the Blind.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
